AS53011.xmlWhitlock (Brand) papersRegister of the Brand Whitlock papers 53011 53011 Finding aid prepared by Theresa BergerHoover Institution Archives
© 2009, 2016
This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on 2018-05-09 14:13:37 -0700 .Finding aid is written in English Describing Archives: A Content Standard
Brand Whitlock papers
1913-1934
Hoover Institution Archives
Whitlock, Brand, 1869-1934.
53011
11.0 linear feet 9 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder
Writings, diaries, scrapbooks, drawings, printed matter, and photographs relating to Belgian-American relations during World War I, the work of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, and the writings of Brand Whitlock.
Boxes 1-8
Shelf 9.13
Boxes 9-12
Shelf 18.03
Box 13
Shelf OS.17
Map case
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1953.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Brand Whitlock was an American author, politician, diplomat, and ambassador to Belgium from 1913 to 1922. After serving as mayor of Toledo, Ohio from 1906 to 1913, Whitlock was appointed ambassador to Belgium by President Woodrow Wilson in 1913. In 1914, Whitlock's diplomatic duties increased significantly when the outbreak of the First World War and subsequent German occupation of Belgium put him in charge of various relief efforts for Belgian citizens. Whitlock's efforts to ensure that food sent by the Committee for Relief in Belgium went directly to Belgian citizens and not German forces, as well as his frequent appeals to German military authorities on behalf of condemned prisoners in Belgium, earned him the nickname Le Ministre Protecteur. In addition to his diplomatic and political efforts, Whitlock published several novels, biographies, articles, and short essays.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Brand Whitlock papers consist of writings, diaries, photographs, albums, scrapbooks, drawings, illustrations, and printed matter relating to Belgian-American relations during World War I, the work of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, and the numerous writings of Brand Whitlock. Several of the writings in the collection appear to be unpublished.
American literature.; Belgium--Foreign relations--United States.; Belgium--History--German occupation, 1914-1918.; Diplomats--United States.; International relief.; United States--Foreign relations--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; Whitlock, Brand, 1869-1934.; Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930)
- Biographical File, 1914-1933, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains clippings, articles, certificates, receipts, and other material related to Whitlock's diplomatic and literary careers.
  - Clippings and magazine articles, 1914-1933, undated (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
    Includes news clippings and magazine features about Whitlock.
  - Social ledger, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Contains a social ledger describing calls made to the American Embassy in Belgium, possibly owned by Whitlock, his wife (Mrs. Whitlock), his mother (also Mrs. Whitlock), or his mother-in-law (Mrs. Brainerd).
  - Miscellaneous, 1926-1928, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Includes Whitlock's bookplates, hotel receipts, and a program for a banquet held in Washington, D.C. in 1928 honoring the King and Queen of Belgium.
  - Oversized, 1914-1924 (Box-folder 12: 1, Box-folder 13: 28)
    Includes additional magazine features about Whitlock (Box 12) as well as a bound certificate of recognition presented to Whitlock on behalf of the Belgian government (Box 13).
- Writings, 1913-1933, undated
  Contains edited manuscripts, notes, prints, and drafts relating to various published and unpublished writings by Whitlock.
  - "The American Quality in American Literature: A Paper to Be Read Before the National Institute of Arts and Letters,", 1915 November (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "Barrett Montgomery's Proposal," manuscript, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - The Buckeyes, manuscript and notes, undated (Box-folder 2: 1-4, Box-folder 1: 7-9)
  - "The City of the Future," address delivered at The Hudson Theatre, 1913 October (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "Courdray,", undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Democracy," manuscript, multiple versions, undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "Francis Rabelais,", undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "Frontispiece," The World's Work, 1915 December (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - J. Hardin and Son, 1923-1928, undated
    - Draft (excerpts), undated (Box-folder 2: 10-11, Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Review, Plain Talk, 1928 May (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - The Delineator, 1923 July-December (Box-folder 12: 2)
      The novel was published one chapter at a time in The Delineator.
  - "Mr. Jefferson,", 1933, undated
    Relates to an unpublished biography of Thomas Jefferson.
    - Manuscript addressed to Miss Mary Chaldecott, undated (Box-folder 3: 3-5)
    - "Notes, documents, pictures, memoranda, and divers,", 1933, undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
      Includes various photos of Colonial Williamsburg dated 1933.
    - Notes, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "Karla,", undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "The Law of the Land," Atlantic Monthly, 1930 August (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Macochee, undated (Box-folder 3: 10-11)
    Includes manuscript excerpts as well as an assumed manuscript addressed to Miss Mary Chaldecott.
  - "Mr. H - A Story," draft, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "Narcisse,", 1931 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Includes published versions and reviews.
  - Notes and drafts, unidentified, undated (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
    Includes drafts, edits, and incomplete manuscripts of works with possible titles such as "The Game" and "A Lincoln Penny." Also includes possible excerpts from The Buckeyes and Walt Whitman: How to Know Him.
  - "Ohio Novel,", undated (Box-folder 4: 5-8)
    Includes various manuscripts, chapter excerpts, and notes for an unfinished novel.
  - "On a Little Traverse Bay," poem, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - "The Place at Table,", undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - "The Portrait of Maria," unpublished manuscript, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - "Progress and [?] in Glasgow," notes and drafts, undated (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - "The Rehabilitation of General Todhunter," Sunday Magazine, 1915 December (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - "The Ribbon," edited drafts, undated (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - "The Sofa: How a Grave Political Crisis Yielded to Feminine Tact," The Argosy, 1931 March (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - "A Son of a Good-For-Nothing: A Satirical Comedy in Four Acts," by Brand Whitlock and Frank Neilson, manuscript, 1914 January-February, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
    Includes related correspondence.
  - The Stranger on the Island (also known as "Beaver Island"), undated
    - Manuscript addressed to Miss Mary Chaldecott, undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Manuscript addressed to Miss Agnes F. Pearson, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Typed, edited draft, undated (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Manuscript and notes, assumed, undated (Box-folder 5: 8-10)
      It is not certain that these pages are part of The Stranger on the Island ("Beaver Island").
  - "Thou Shalt Not Kill,", undated (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Transplanted, undated (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
    Includes typed manuscript with edits as well as a folder titled "Notes for the Countess of Granvallon," the novel's original title.
  - "The White Slave in America," The English Review, 1914 February (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Untitled manuscript 1, undated (Box-folder 6: 6)
    Contains pages of an untitled manuscript, possibly Whitlock's biography of Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette.
  - Untitled manuscript 2, undated (Box-folder 6: 7-8, Box-folder 7: 1-3)
    Contains notes and pages related to an untitled manuscript, possibly J. Hardin and Son.
- Correspondence, 1914-1934
  Contains letters and notes of gratitude from Belgian children, teachers, and citizens as well as some business-related correspondence. Several letters include children's artwork. Material in English, French, and Flemish.
  - General, 1914, 1921, undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Baelin, Renée, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Baron Eugène de Moffarts, et. al, 1915 January (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Baué, Raphael, 1915 February (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Bertha, Laurent, et. al, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Book of notes from Belgian citizens, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    Contains notes from Belgian citizens expressing their gratitude towards relief efforts conducted by the United States.
  - Chérer, Mouriette, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - China, Aline, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Clarkson, 1934 March (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Collard, Jean, circa 1915 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Collard, Wilhelmina, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Comité Regional d'Alimentation, 1915 February (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Commission for Relief in Belgium / Lace Department of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 7: 16)
    Includes correspondence, notes, and receipts addressed to Brand Whitlock and Mrs. Whitlock.
  - Coussaint, Rosa, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Dautremont, Albine, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Deglime, Léonie, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Descotte, Emilie, circa 1915 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - Englebert, Eveline, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 21)
  - Friends of Belgium, 1925 April (Box-folder 7: 22)
  - G., Céline, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 23)
  - Genin, Louisa, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 24)
  - George, 1919 October (Box-folder 7: 25)
  - Guernier [?], Anaïs, 1915 March (Box-folder 7: 26)
  - Henrottin, Maria, et. al, 1915 February (Box-folder 7: 27)
  - Henry, Pier, et. al, 1915 February (Box-folder 7: 28)
  - Herbriet, Paul, 1915 February (Box-folder 7: 29)
  - Lambot [?], Yvonne, circa 1915 (Box-folder 7: 30)
  - Leoloux, André, 1915 February (Box-folder 7: 31)
  - "Letters of gratitude,", circa 1915 (Box-folder 7: 32, Box-folder 8: 1)
    Contains letters of gratitude from Belgian school teachers and citizens thanking Whitlock and the Commission for Relief in Belgium.
  - "Letters from children in Brussels,", 1914 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    Contains letters from children in Brussels thanking Whitlock for his relief efforts in Belgium.
  - Lison, Armand, et. al, circa 1915 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Louis, E., 1915 February (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Muller, André, 1915 February (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Naveaux, Rosa, 1915 March (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Orìanne, Joseph, et. al, 1915 February (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Raison, Georges, et. al, 1915 February (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Rosa, Adam, 1915 March (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Toussaint, Ernestine, 1915 March (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Vander Elst, Philippe, 1915 February (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Vanderry, circa 1915 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Wauters, Henri, 1915 January (Box-folder 8: 13)
- Writings by Others, 1914, undated
  Contains two unidentified journals as well as collected poems by Witter Bynner and A. E. Houseman.
  - Unidentified journals, 1914 (Box-folder 8: 14-15)
    Includes two unidentified journals possibly written by Whitlock's mother-in-law (Mrs. Brainerd), his wife (Mrs. Whitlock), or his mother (also Mrs. Whitlock). The journals describe life and events in Belgium in 1914.
  - Bynner, Witter, undated (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - Houseman, A. E., undated (Box-folder 8: 17)
- Scrapbooks, 1914-1933, undated (Box 10)
  Contains two untitled scrapbooks, one with war-related clippings, the other with cartoons and illustrations pasted together to create humorous scenes depicting social and political commentary on current events.
- Photographs, 1905-1929
  Contains prints, autographed portraits, and a photo album.
  - General, 1905-1929 (Box-folder 8: 18)
    Includes autographed portraits of European leaders and diplomats.
  - Album, circa 1914-1918 (Box-folder 8: 19, Box 11)
    Includes an album with photos of Whitlock, his family, and several unidentified people, presumably from the family's time in Belgium. Folder 8: 19 contains loose photographs from the album.
  - Oversized, circa 1914-1918, undated (Box-folder 12: 3-4, Box-folder 13: 1-26)
    Contains various prints and mounted portraits. Subjects include Brand Whitlock and family, the American Embassy in Belgium, local sculptures and artwork, and portraits of European military and political figures, many with signatures and inscriptions addressed to Whitlock.
- Drawings and Illustrations, 1916-1928, undated
  Contains sketches, illustrations, and watercolors, some with artists' signatures and dedications to Whitlock.
  - Sketches by H. Lemaire, 1918 (Box 11)
    Contains prints of portrait sketches of European officials by H. Lemaire in original foldering.
  - Sketches of military figures, 1916-1918, undated (Box-folder 12: 5-7)
    Includes sketches and watercolor paintings of military figures, some with artists' signatures and inscriptions to Whitlock.
  - Map of Brussels, undated (Box-folder 12: 8)
    Contains a printed map of Brussels with various landmarks identified by hand.
  - Watercolors by F. Houget, 1928 (Box-folder 12: 17)
    Contains a collection of watercolor paintings by F. Houget depicting Belgian officials and politicians playing golf. Includes the artist's signature and an inscription to Whitlock.
  - Oversized, undated (Box-folder 13: 27, Map case)
    Includes sketches dedicated to Whitlock by A. Baertsoen and two unknown artists. The map case contains a large sketch entitled "La Resistance," depicting what appears to be Lady Liberty warding off a black bird, as well as a sketch by A. Baertsoen depicting a snow-covered village in Belgium (1921).
- Printed Matter, circa 1913-1934
  Contains clippings, articles, sheet music, postcards, and other material.
  - "Literary Notes,", 1913, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 8: 20)
    Contains clippings, articles, theater programs, and other material related to popular works of literature.
  - Miscellaenous, 1913-1933 (Box-folder 9: 1-6, Box-folder 8: 21)
    Includes clippings, conference proceedings, newspapers, magazines, postcards, travel brochures, and other material. Subjects include European travel, Cannes, Belgium, and the war from 1914-1918.
  - Oversized, 1913-1934 (Box-folder 12: 9-16)
    Includes magazines, newspapers, event programs, and sheet music in French and English.